Roni Sarig Collection, 1984-2007, bulk 2000-2007 SC 148
Archives of African American Music and Culture
- 2. Interviews (audio), undated; 40 audio recordings
  - 2.1. Interviews conducted by Roni Sarig, undated; 34 Audio Files
    - Interviews with MC Shy-D, Missy Elliott, and Willie D, undated; CASS 2181; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      MC Shy D, Missy Elliott and Willie D interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      A continuation of Sarig's interview with Atlanta artist MC Shy D (aka Peter Jones), who talks about his album "The Comeback" and some more of his recent works. Missy Elliott talks about her childhood in Virginia, what led to her into music, her experiences in an R&B group, and going solo after the group disbanded; she explains her unique sound and how it came about; the benefits and detriments of living in various places while in the music business; and her experiences working with Pharrell, as well as her experiences signing other artists. Willie D describes his childhood in Houston, how he got into music by participating in rap contests before eventually joining the Geto Boys, the hip hop influences at that time, the various issues that triggered disputes within the Geto Boys and led to the group disbanding.
    - Interviews with Ying Yang Twins (D-Roc and Kaine), Trick Daddy, Ted Lucas and Unknown, undated; CASS 2182; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/8515645x6s
      Ying Yang Twins, Trick Daddy, Ted Lucas, and Charles Young interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      D-Roc talks about his love of music and his beginnings in music writing and performing. He talks a bit about his childhood before becoming a member of the Ying Yang Twins. They then discuss the labels they went through and the people that they worked with. Kaine talks about his childhood and how he became a member of the group. Trick Daddy continues showing Sarig around his house, explaining the significance of various items that he owns. Trick Daddy then describes how he has changed as he has aged and how it has affected his music. Trick finishes by talking about his probation, the reason he went to jail, and his time away from drugs. Sarig and Ted discuss Trick Daddy's evolution in both his music and his private life. They talk more about Trick Daddy's probation and reason for being arrested. Ted then explains his time in the music scene in Florida. He talks about various artists, like the 2 Live Crew and other artists that focused on bass music. They finish by discussing the importance of Miami Hip-Hop and bass music to the music industry as a whole. Charles explains how he got started in the music business back in 1985 with his label Suntown Records. Charles describes how he raised Trick Daddy since Trick was 7 years old and how he helped him into the music business. Charles then describes how Trick Daddy has changed over the years.
    - Interviews with Gregory D, Bo Crane and DJ Smurf, undated; CASS 2183; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/w52j237b5m
      Gregory D, Bo Crane and DJ Smurf interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Gregory D talks about working with Mannie Fresh, getting signed to D&D Records, and releasing their first records. He discusses working with Brian Smith as a part of an independent record UZI to release their next record before moving on to Yo! Records. Bo talks about coming to Florida to get a doctorate in Music Theory and Composition, part-timing as a disk jockey part time. He ended up dropping out of school and kept trying to make a living making music in Miami. Bo explains how he started making music for clubs and record labels, such as TK, in the late 70's. They discuss the genesis of bass music and the emergence and successes of different types of bass music, like car audio. Sarig and Crane continue discussing the popularity of car audio before finishing the interview talking about the artists and labels that were the key movers of the bass music genre. DJ Smurf talks about his biographical information, when he moved to Atlanta, and how he started a career as a DJ. They talk about the point bass music became a prominent genre in Atlanta and MC Shy D's influence. Smurf describes his time working with Ichiban, rapping some of his own music, and going independent.
    - Interview with Clipse (brothers Pusha T and Malice), undated; CASS 2184; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/940791tk6n
      Pusha T and Malice of Clipse interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Sarig talks with the members of rap duo Clipse and their group, Re-Up Gang. They discuss contract issues that Clipse has been facing due to the changes at Arista and Jive Records. They also discuss The Neptunes' label, Star Trak, which released Clipse's first record. Because of the problems with Jive, Clipse has formed a new group called Re-Up Gang with Ab-Liva and Sandman; they discuss their first mixtape. Because of the inclusion of the two rappers from Philadelphia, they feel more connected to East Coast rap styles than southern styles. They discuss the artistry of using other people's beats and the influence of "Grindin'". Sarig continues his discussion with Clipse. They talk about different styles of hip-hop, saying that the East Coast style is much more lyrically-driven, and express displeasure about how hip-hop is losing its diversity. They continue the discussion of problems surrounding their contract with Jive from Side A of the same tape.In a phone interview with Clipse, he details a recent press release from Jive about their new record. In a phone interview with an unidentified person, he discusses Chris Lighty and the mismanagement of Clipse.
    - Interviews with Fresh Kid Ice, Neil Case and Billy Hines, undated; CASS 2185; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/613m90g18r
      Fresh Kid Ice, Neil Case and Billy Hines interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Fresh Kid Ice explains his and Luke's arrest that led directly to the obscenity trial. The arrest and lead-up to the trial made it more difficult for them to perform, while helping increase the 2 Live Crew's record sales. Fresh Kid Ice then describes how the obscenity trial and public attention affected his personal life and the 2 Lives Crew's music, ending on the relationship between the group and Luke. Sarig and Neil discuss Neil's childhood and early life in Jamaica, leading up to his time working at Soundshine Productions in Fort Lauderdale in 1988. They discuss the connection between Miami Bass music and Jamaican music. Neil explains why Bass music was more attractive in the South compared to the North. The car audio aspect, which was a large factor, is also discussed. They then discuss the cultural bigotry between the music from the North and South. They briefly finish up Neil's interview. Sarig and Billy talk about Billy's childhood, reasons for moving to Florida from Tennessee, his previous jobs, and his transition to working in the music industry. They talk about the record store Billy owned and what kinds of music he sold. Billy explains how he brought a regular/helper at his store, Adrian, to the label, and let him make his own track ("Bass Rock Express"). This is the beginning to Adrian's career as MC A.D.E. Billy talks about his other artists, including MC Shy D and New Beginnings. They talk about what Billy has been doing since the store closed, before ending with a discussion on the important forces behind bass music.
    - Interviews with 8Ball and John "J-Dogg" Shaw, undated; CASS 2186; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/1687527j9d
      8ball and John "J-Dogg" Shaw interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Roni Sarig and 8Ball discuss 8Ball's musical influences and the Memphis style. They describe the Memphis sound and its connection to crunk music, its connection to other areas like Atlanta and Houston, as well as 8Ball and MJG's early career and some of their records. A second interview with the writer J-Dogg starts with a discussion about the music scene in Memphis. Roni Sarig talks with John "J-Dogg" Shaw, a writer and employee of Select-O-Hit Records, about rap and hip hop in Memphis. They discuss how the culture of Memphis influenced the musical style, and how the racial tensions and mismanagement of Stax Records led to a gap between earlier Black artists and hip hop. They also discuss the earliest rap and hip hop releases from Memphis, as well as how East Coast and Miami styles influenced the Memphis sound.
    - Interviews with Boss King, Al Kapone, and Gangsta Pat., undated; CASS 2187; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/x71960383n
      Memphis artists Boss King, Al Kapone and Gangsta Pat interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Roni Sarig and Boss King, along with Wes Phillips, discuss the rap scene in Memphis. They talk about Memphis' musical and cultural history, the importance of Stax Records, and early artists like Gangsta Pat and Al Kapone. They also discuss problems surrounding Three 6 Mafia, as well as upcoming new artists like Yo Gotti. Sarig and Kapone discuss Kapone's early musical experiences and influences, and early Memphis rappers, particularly Gangsta Pat. Pat joins the interview partway through (continued on Side B). Roni Sarig and Gangsta Pat discuss Pat's early musical influences and career, as well as the musical vibe and history of Memphis. They also talk about other Memphis artists like 8Ball and Three 6 Mafia, as well as Pat's time in Atlanta. Sarig and Kapone talk about Kapone's early career, first songs and albums, and his early record labels
      (Kapone interview continued on CASS 2188).
    - Interviews with Al Kapone, Devin Steel, and Freddy Hydro, undated; CASS 2188; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/c18d47430v
      Memphis artists Al Kapone, Devin Steel and Freddy Hydro interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Roni Sarig and Al Kapone discuss his career and the Memphis sound. They talk about Kapone's early career and sound, his decision to create his own record label, and his involvement with the film Hustle and Flow. [Devin Steel?] and Sarig talk about radio in Memphis, early DJs, and the mixtape culture. Sarig and [Devin Steel?] discuss the Memphis scene. They talk about the film Hustle and Flow, as well as the radio music scene in Memphis during the 1990s and how it affected music and artists. They discuss the Memphis sound, including whether Three 6 Mafia's sound is typical for Memphis and how Memphis and other southern styles are connected. They also talk about the club scene and dance styles. Sarig and Hydro discuss the Memphis music scene and the relationship between different artists, particularly focusing on Three 6 Mafia.
    - Interviews with Matt Sonzala and Tony Mercedes, undated; CASS 2189; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/j92g258r0p
      Matt Sonzala and Tony Mercedes interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Matt Sonzala, a Houston-based journalist, talks about the influence of hip hop and hardcore rap on the Houston music scene from the 1980s to the late 1990s. Includes discussions about the South Park Coalition, Geto Boys and their fluctuating member base, DJ Screw, and a comparison of the South Side of Houston and the Screwed Up Click with the North Side, where Michael Watts was prominent. Matt discusses drug use in the 1990s and its effect on rap music at the time, popular rap artists including UGK, Paul Wall, Slim Thug, South Park Mexican, Devin the Dude and Odd Squad. Discussion of Tony Mercedes' career, his ownership of Club Mercedes in Augusta, Georgia, his involvement with the music business, the popularity of Duice's debut single "Dazzey Duks" which he co-produced, and the popularity of bass music.
      Rap (Music)--Southern States; African American sound recording executives and producers
    - Interviews with DXJ and Fresh Kid Ice, undated; CASS 2190; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/940791tk7z
      Florida artists DXJ and Fresh Ice Kid interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Sarig discusses the history of bass music with DXJ, a DJ (of many names) based in Miami; the most prominent artists and the trend at the time to start labels and music distribution centers; the peak of Miami bass and eventual shift into different sub-genres, including booty music and car audio bass. Roni Sarig and DXJ continue their interview about Miami bass music, including car audio bass, "good" bass music, and influences from reggaeton and other cultures. Fresh Kid Ice and Roni Sarig talk about the formation of 2 Live Crew, the popularity of their first singles, their eventual move to Florida, signing to Macola Records, working with DJ Luke, their transformation of the Miami bass sound and motivations for making booty music, obscenity charges and the legal consequences of including explicit lyrics in purchasable and performable music.
    - Interviews with KLC and Lil Flip, undated; CASS 2191; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/b88q37ww5k
      KLC and Lil' Flip interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      KLC (aka Craig Lawson of New Orleans) interview is not audible; only Sarig's questions are recorded. Roni Sarig interviews Houston native Lil' Flip about his musical career as a rapper and producer, the DJ Screw generation, his upbringing, his relationship to the Sucka Free Label, his album "I Need Mine," the various artists featured on his albums, his musical projects and business ventures, and his attempts to lead Houston into a new era of hip hop. The interview continues with a brief discussion of Flip's early years and education; a breakdown of various songs and the artists that he chose to feature including members of the Screwed Up Click; his goals and ambitions, and the image he wants to build going forward.
    - Interviews with DJ Jubilee, Speech, and Mr. Mixx, undated; CASS 2193; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/q27z60f47w
      DJ Jubilee, Speech, and Mr. Mixx are interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      DJ Jubilee (aka Jerome Temple) of New Orleans talks about his background, the creation and evolution of the bounce style, the artists who create bounce music, the popularity of "Triggaman," the labels Cash Money and No Limit and their influence on New Orleans music. Speech (aka Todd Thomas) of the Atlanta rap group Arrested Development talks about his education and family life, and how his experiences in Tennessee influenced his musical career in a powerful way and were expressed in his first single, "Tennessee." Discussion of Arrested Development's focus on Afro and Southern centric music and themes, the popularity of their first single "Tennessee;" failure of EMI to promote second album; his company Vagabond that promotes newer groups; and the divide between "Black Mecca" African American kids vs "Organized Noise" teens. Mr. Mixx (aka David Hobbs) of Miami talks about his life in the Air Force leading up to his meeting with the group that would eventually form 2 Live Crew; their hit record "Throw the D" and its influence on bass music as a genre, and Mr. Mixx's eventual lawsuit against Luke for song theft.
    - Interviews with L Rocc, R. Prophet and Devin the Dude, undated; CASS 2196; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/5547721q1v
      L Rocc, R. Prophet and Devin the Dude interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      L Rocc talks to Sarig about his time performing as an original member of The Chronicle. L Rocc talks about Jermaine Dupri signing him to So So Def Recordings, while still performing with Lil John in his free time. In R. Prophet's interview with Sarig, Prophet describes living in Oakland and reasons for his family moving to Kentucky. They talk about the other members of Nappy Roots, where they came from, and how wound up meeting in Louisville, Kentucky. Prophet talks about meeting the rest of members in college, getting into rapping together, and forming the complete Nappy Roots. Prophet continues talking about the official formation of Nappy Roots, dropping their first independent CD in 1998, and getting signed to Atlantic Records. Prophet talks about their Nappy roots influence to the state of Kentucky and finishes the interview talking about the album Nappy Roots is trying to release after leaving Atlantic Records. In Devin the Dude's interview with Roni Sarig, Devin discusses the beginnings of hip hop coming out of Texas, Odd Squad getting signed to Rap A Lot, and then going solo. Finally, they discuss the most significant/influential artists that have come out of Houston and the influences that made Houston such a strong force in the music industry.
    - Interview with Joe (DJ PappaWheelie Gonzalez), undated; CASS 2197; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/089227nw1m
      Joe interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Joe discusses the history and evolution of the Miami bass sound, the role of DJ Magic Mike and his influence on the bass music genre, Bass Station and Suntown Records, the roles of producer Clay D, Mannie Fresh, Chaszey Chess, Cool Rock and Gregory D, and the equipment used in bass music production. Joe discusses the beginnings of Henry Stone's TK Records in Florida, the label's bankruptcy and merger into Sunnyview Records; Florida's 4 Sight Records and its role in the Miami bass scene; Florida's electro music and rap pioneers including Pretty Tony and DXJ, and the influence of Jamaican DJ's including King Sporty.
      Rap (Music)--Southern States
    - Interviews with John Abbey, Tony Rock, and DJ Jubilee, undated; CASS 2199; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/465544cs1k
      John Abbey, Tony M.F. Rock, and DJ Jubilee are interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      John Abbey (continuation from 2209) discusses several of the rap artists on Ichiban/Wrap, including DJ Smurf, Willie D, Kilo, and 95 South, as well as some of the legal problems with record labels and artists being signed to multiple labels at a time. They also talk about why Ichiban went bankrupt. In the second interview, Tony M.F. Rock (Anthony Durham), a former rapper from Atlanta details his early career and successes, as well as his influences and friendship with fellow Atlanta rapper, DJ Shy D. Tony M.F. Rock discusses his relationship with DJ Shy D, their early group Ultimate Krush, and the legal troubles surrounding Luke Records. They also talk about Rock's singles and album Let Me Take You to the Rock House. In the second interview, Sarig talks with New Orleans' DJ Jubilee. They discuss Jubilee's childhood and early career with Fellas DJs. They also discuss early New Orleans rappers, including The Ninja Crew and The Low Down Boys (continued on Cass 2193).
      Technical Notes: Distortion in Rock interview
    - Interviews with Jermaine Dupri and Ian Burke, undated; CASS 2200; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/r76f06h93x
      Jermaine Dupri and Ian Burke are interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Jermaine Dupri discusses his role in the music industry, his career as an artist and record label owner, the various artists he has produced, and his experiences with Sony and Virgin Records. Ian Burke talks about his reasons for moving to Atlanta, what sparked his interest in being a part of the music industry, and the factors that played a role in developing the music scene in Atlanta. Ian Burke discusses his introduction to the music business, briefly managing the Atlanta hip hop group Arrested Development, his role in forming the group TLC, working with the Dungeon Family at Rico Wade's studio, working with Organized Noize, moving to an A&R position at Elektra and eventually working at ASCAP in Atlanta.
    - Interview with Trick Daddy, undated; CASS 2201; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/v53j92hh50
      Trick Daddy interviewed by Roni Sarig, author of the book, The Third Coast: Outkast, Timbaland, and How Hip Hop Became a Southern Thing.
      Trick Daddy begins the interview by talking about the vision he has for his upcoming album before taking a step back to talk about the various people he has worked with, including his brother who will be the president of their new company. He talks about his childhood growing up in Liberty City and speaks on his multiple times in prison as a teenager. After picking up rapping in prison, he chose to make it a career path after being from prison. They move on to discussing about the music scene in Miami, Luke's place in that space, and Trick's involvement with Luke before his eventual signing with Slip-N-Slide. Trick Daddy talks a bit about Trina and his involvement with her getting into the music business. Then they speak on the success Trick Daddy has had after signing with Slip-N-Slide Records. This interview is a continuation of Trick Daddy's interview by Roni Sarig. Trick daddy begins this side by talking about his refusal to stop using Thug for the title of his albums and songs and the reasons for his stance. He then plays Sarig the songs from his album Thug Matrimony, discussing some of the lyrics and themes in his music. Trick Daddy explains why he dislike rapping about his material items and finishes the interview by giving Roni a tour of his house, conversing about various topics.
    - Interviews with Lil Ru, Pastor Troy, and the Filthy Boys, undated; CASS 2203; Sarig, Roni (Writer on music); 1 Audiocassette: digital + 1 index
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/q57n69nc8d